<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Remonstrance of grievances presented to His Most Excellent Majestie in the behalfe of the Catholicks of Ireland</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58535</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">9390700</idno>
  <idno type="VID">42945</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264209815</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R989</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26217</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">09390700</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58535)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 42945)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1314:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Remonstrance of grievances presented to His Most Excellent Majestie in the behalfe of the Catholicks of Ireland</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Bourke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Waterford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Catholics --  Ireland.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Anti-Catholicism --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Persecution --  Ireland.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-10 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:42945:1"/>
            <p>A REMONSTRANCE OF GRIEVANCES PRESEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his most Excellent Majestie, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he behalfe of the Catholicks of IRELAND.</p>
            <figure>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>NI SOIT <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> MAL <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>DIEV ET MON DROIT</p>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at <hi>VVaterford</hi> by <hi>Thomas Bourke,</hi> Printe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the Confederate Catholicks of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Anno Dom. 1643.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:42945:2"/>
            <p>THis remonstrance was delivered, by the Lord Viscount Gormonstowne, Sir Lucas Dillon Knight, Sir Robert Talbot Barronnet, &amp; Iohn VValsh Esquire, thereunto authorised, by the Confederate Catholicks of Ireland, to his Majesties Commissioners, at the Towne of Trim, in the County of Meath, on the <hi>17.</hi> of March <hi>1642▪</hi> to be presented to his most Excellent Majestie.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:42945:2"/>
            <head>TO THE KINGS MOST EXCELLENT MAIESTIE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ost gracious Soveraigne, Wee your Majesties most dutifull, &amp; loyall subjects, the Catholicks of your Highnesse kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> being necessitated to take armes for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of our Religion, the mayntenance of your Majesties rights, &amp; prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atives, the naturall &amp; just defence of our lives &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>states, &amp; the liberties of our country; have often <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ince the beginning of these troubles attempted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o present our humble complaint unto your Royal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iew, but were frustrated of our hopes therein, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he power and vigilancie of our adversaries (the now Lords justices &amp; other ministers of State in this kingdome) who by the assistance of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant party in <hi>England</hi> now in Armes against your Royall person, with lesse difficulty to attaine
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:42945:3"/> the bad ends they proposed to themselves of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irpating our Religion &amp; Nation, hitherto debar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red us of any accesse to your Majesties justice, which occasioned the effusion of much innocent bloud &amp; other mischiefes in this your kingdome, that otherwise might well be prevented. And whereas of late notice was sent unto us of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission granted by your Majesty to the right ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable the Lord Marques of <hi>Ormond</hi> and others authorizing them, to heare what we shall say, or propound, &amp; the same to transmit unto your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty in writing, which your Majest<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es gracious an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> princely favour, we find to be accompanied with these words; viz. (<hi>albeit we doe extreamly detest the odious rebellion which the recusants of</hi> Ireland <hi>have without ground o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> colour raised against us our Crowne and dignitie</hi>) which words, wee doe in all humilitie conceive to have proceeded from the misrepresen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of our adversaries; and therfore do protest, we have been, therin maliciously traduced to your Majestie, having never entertayned any rebellious thought against your Majestie, your Crowne, or dignitie, but alwayes have beene and ever will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue your Majesties most faithfull and loyall sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and doe most humbly beseech your Majesty so to owne, &amp; avow us, and as such wee present un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:42945:3"/> your Majesty these ensuing grievances, and causes of the present distempers.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>In primis,</hi> the Catholicks of this kingdome whom no reward could invite, no persecution in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force to forsake that Religion professed by them, and their ancestors for thirteene hundred yeares or there abouts, are since the second yeare of the raigne of Queen <hi>Eliz</hi> made incapable of places of honor, or trust in Church or Common-wealth, their Nobles become contemptible their Gentry debarred from learning in Vniversities, or publick Schooles within this kingdome, their yonger bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers put by all manner of imployment in their native countrie, and necessitated eyther to live in ignorance and contempt at home, or (to their great discomfort, &amp; impoverishment of the land) to seeke education and fortune abroad; misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes made incident to the said Catholicks of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> onely (their numbers, qualitie, and loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie considered) of all the Nations in Christen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p n="2">2 Secondly, that by this incapacitie, which in respect of their Religion was imposed upon the said Catholicks, men of meane condition &amp; qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie for the most part, were in this kingdome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in places of greatest honor and trust, who,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:42945:4"/> being to begin a fortune built it of the Ruines of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Catholicke Natives, at all times lying open to be discountenanced, and wrought upon, and who (because they would seeme to be carefull of the government) did from time to time, suggest false &amp; malicious matters against them, the said Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, to render them suspected and odious in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> from which ungrounded informations and their many other ill Offices, these mischiefes have befallen the Catholickes of <hi>Ireland:</hi> First the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions given to all the graces, and favours that your Majestie, or your late Royall Father promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed or intended to the Natives of this kingdome. Secondly the procuring of false inquisitions upon faygned Titles of their estates against many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares possession, and no travers, or petition of right admitted thereunto, and Iurors denying to find such Offices, were censured even to their publicke infamy, &amp; ruine of their estates, the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thereof being against their consciences and cleere evidences, and nothing must stand against such Offices taken of great and considerable parts of the kingdome, but Letters-patents under the great Seale, And if Letters-patents were produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, (as in most cases they were) none must bee allowed, valid, not yet fought to be legally avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:42945:4"/> So that of late times by the underhand wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Sir <hi>VVilliam Parsons</hi> now one of your Lords Iustices here, and the arbitrary illegall po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the two impeached Iudges in Parliament, and others drawne by their advice and counsell, one hundred and fiftie Letters-patents were avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in one morning, which course continued un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till all the Patents of the kingdome, to a few were by them, and their associats declared voyd, such was the care those ministers had of your Majesties great Seale, being the publicke faith of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, this way of service, in shew onely preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for your Majesty, proved to your diservice, and the immoderate and too timely advancement of the said ministers of state, and their adherents, &amp; too neere the utter ruine of the said Catholicks.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That whereas your Majesties late Royall Father King <hi>Iames,</hi> having a princely and father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly care of this kingdome, was graciously pleased, to grant severall large and beneficiall Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons under the great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> and severall instructions, and Letters under his privie Signet, for the passing and securing of the estates of his subjects here by Letters-patents under the great Seale, and Letters-patents accordingly were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of passed, fines payed, old rents increased, and new
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:42945:5"/> rents reserved to the Crowne, And the said lat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King was further graciously pleased, at severall times to send divers honourable persons of inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, knowledge and experience, to examine the grievances of this kingdome, and to setle and esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h a course for redresse thereof. And whereas your Majesty was graciously pleased, in the fourth yeare of your raigne, to vouchsafe a favorable hearing to the grievances presented unto you by Agents from this kingdome, and thereupon d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d grant many graces and favours unto your subjects thereof, for securitie of their estates, and redress<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, for remove of those heavy pressures under which they have long groaned, which acts of justice, and grace extended to this people; by your Maje<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tie and your said Royall Father did afford them great content, yet such was, and is yet, the immortall hatred of some of the said ministers of state, and especially of the said Sir <hi>VViliam Parsons,</hi> the said impeached iudges and their adherents to any wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare and happinesse of this Nation, and their am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, to make themselves still greater and richer, by the totall ruine and extirpation of this people, that under pretence of your Majesties service the publicke faith involved in those grants was viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and the grace and goodnesse intended by two
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:42945:5"/> glorious Kings successively to a faithfull people, made unprofitable.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The illegall, arbitrary, and unlawfull pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the said Sir <hi>VVilliam Parsons,</hi> and of the said impeached Iudges, and their adherents, and instruments in the Court of Wards, and the many wilfully erroneous decrees, and judgements of that Court, by which the heires of Catholicke Noble-men, and other Catholicks were most cruelly, and tyrannically dealt withall, destroyed in their estates, and bred in dissolution, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, their Parents debts unsatisfied, their Sisters and younger brothers left wholy unprovided for, the ancient and appearing tenures of <hi>mesne</hi> Lords unregarded, estates valid in Law, and made for valuable considerations, avoyded against Law, and the whole Land filled up with the frequent swarmes of Escheators, Feodaries, Pursevants, and others by authority of that Court.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The said Catholicks notwithstanding the heavie pressures before mentioned, and other grievances in part represented to your Majestie by the late Committees of both houses of Parliament of this kingdome, whereunto they humbly desire that relation he had and redresse obtayned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in did readily and without reluctation or repyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:42945:6"/> contribute to all the Subsidies, Loanes, and other extraordinarie grants made to your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie in this kingdome, since the beginning of your Raigne amounting unto well-neere one Million of pounds, over and above your Majesties Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, both certayne, and casuall: And although the said Catholickes were in Parliament and other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise the most forward in granting the said sums, and did beare nine parts of ten in the payments thereof, yet such was the power of their adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries, and the advantage they gayned by the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie of their continuall adresses to your Majestie, to increase their reputation in getting in of those monyes, and their authority in the distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution thereof to your Majesties great diservice, that they assumed to themselves to be procurers thereof, and represented the said Catholicks as obstinate and refractarie.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The Army raised for your Majesties service here at the great charge of the kingdome was dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded, by the pressing importunitie of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant party in <hi>England,</hi> not giving way that your Majesty should take advice therein with the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament here, alleadging the said army was popish, and therefore not to be trusted: And although the world could witnesse the unwarrantable; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exempled
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:42945:6"/> invasion, made by the malignant party of the Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> upon your Majesties Honor, rights, prerogatives, and principall flower of your Crowne, And that the said Sir <hi>VVilliam Parsons,</hi> Sir <hi>Adam Loftus</hi> knight your Majesties vice-treasurer of this kingdome and other their adherents, did declare that an Army of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Scots was to arrive in this kingdome to force the said Catholickes to change their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that <hi>Ireland</hi> could never doe well with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a rebellion, to the end the remayne of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives thereof, might be extirpated, and wagers were layd at generall Asseizes, and publicke mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, by some of them, then, and now imployed in places of great profit, and trust in this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that within one yeare no Catholicke should be left in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and that they saw the ancient, and unquestionable priviledges of the Parliament of <hi>Ireland</hi> unjustly, and against Law incroached up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the orders, acts and proceedings of both houses of Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> in sending for, and questioning to, and in, that Parliament the members of the Parliament of this kingdome, sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Parliament here, And that by speeches, and orders Printed by authority of both houses in <hi>England,</hi> it was declared, that <hi>Ireland</hi> was bound
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:42945:7"/> by the Statutes made in <hi>England,</hi> if named, which is contrary to knowne truth, and the Lawes here setled, for foure hundred yeares and upwards. And that the said Catholickes were throughly infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, of the protestation made by both houses of Parliament of <hi>England</hi> against Catholickes, and of their intentions to introduce Lawes for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation of Catholicke religion in the three king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and that they had certaine notice of the cruell and bloudy execution of Priests there, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for being priests, and that your Majesties mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and power could not prevaile with them, to save the life of one condemned Priest, and that the Catholickes of <hi>England</hi> being of their owne flesh and bloud, must suffer or depart the Land, and consequently others not of so neere a relation to them, if bound by their Statutes, and within their power. These motives, although very strong, and powerfull, to produce apprehensions and feares in the said Catholickes, did not prevaile with them to take defensive Armes, much lesse offensive, they still expecting that your Majestie in your high wisedome, might be able in a short time, to apply seasonable cures, and apt remedies unto those evils and innovations.</p>
            <p n="7">7 That the Committees of the Lords and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:42945:7"/> Commons of this kingdome, having attended your Majesty for the space of nine Moneths, your Majesty was graciously pleased (notwithstanding, your then weighty and urgent affaires in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi>) to receive, and very often with great patience to heare their grievances, and many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates thereof at large, during which debates, the said Lords-Iustices, &amp; some of your privie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of this kingdome and their adherents, by their malicious and untrue informations convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to some ministers of state in <hi>England</hi> (who since are declared of the malignant party) and by the continuall solicitation of others of the said privie Counsell gone to <hi>England</hi> of purpose, to crosse &amp; give impediment unto the justice, and grace your Majesty was inclyned to afford to your subjects of this Realme; did as much as in them lay hinder the obtayning of any redresse for the said grievan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and not prevayling therein with your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stie, as they expected, have by their Letters and instruments, laboured with many leading mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Parliament there, to give stop, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption thereunto, and likewise transmitted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Majesty, and some of the state of <hi>England,</hi> sundry, misconstructions, &amp; misrepresentations of the proceedings, and actions of your Parliament
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:42945:8"/> of this your kingdome, and thereby endeavoured to possesse your Majesty, of an evill opinion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and that the said Parliament had no power of Indicature in Capitall causes (which is an essenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all part of Parliament) thereby ayming at the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punitie of some of them, and others who were then impeached of high Treason, and at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction of this Parliament. But the said Lords-Iustices and privie counsell, observing that no art, or practise of theirs, could be powerfull to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw your Majesties grace and good intentions from this people, and that the redresse granted of some principall grievances was to be passed, as acts in Parliament. The said Lords-Iustices, and their adherents, with the height of malice envying the good union; long before setled, and continued be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the members of the house of Commons, and their good correspondencie with the Lords, left nothing unattempted, which might raise dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord and disunion in the said house, and by some of themselves, and some instruments of theirs in the said Commons house, private meetings of great numbers of the said house were appointed, of purpose, to raise distinction of Nation, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, by meanes whereof a faction was made there, which tended much to the disquiet of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:42945:8"/> house, and disturbance of your Majesties, and the publicke service. And after certaine knowledge that the said Committees were by the waterside in <hi>England</hi> with sundry important, &amp; beneficiall Bils, and other graces to be passed, as acts in that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of purpose to prevent the same, the said faction by the practise of the said Lords-Iustices and some of the said privie Counsell, and their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, in tumultuous, and disorderly manner, on the seventh of <hi>August</hi> 1641. and on severall dayes before, cryed for an adjournement of the house, and being overvoted by the voyces of the more moderate part, the said Lords-Iustices and their adherents tould severall honorable Peeres, that if they did not adjourne the Lords house on that day, being Saturday, that they would them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves prorogue, or adjourne the Parliament on the next Monday following, by meanes whereof, and of great numbers of proxies of Noblemen not estated, nor at any time resident in this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (which is destructive to the libertie and freedome of parliament here) the Lords house was on the said seventh day of <hi>August</hi> adjourned, and the house of Commons by occasion thereof and of the faction aforesaid, adjourned soone after, by which meanes those Bils, and graces according
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:42945:9"/> your Majesties intention, and the great expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and the longing desires of your people could not then passe as Acts of parliament. Within a few dayes after this fatall, and inforced adjourne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the said Committees arrived at <hi>Dublin,</hi> with their di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>patch from your Majesty, and presented the sai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e to the said Lords-Iustices and Councell, expressing a right sense of the said adjournement, and besought their Lordships for the satisfaction of the people; to require short heads of that part of the dispatch, wherin your Majesty did appeare, in the best manner, unto your people, might be suddainly conveyed unto all the partes of the kingdome, attested by the said Lords-Iustices, to prevent dispayre or misunderstanding, this was promised to be done, and an instrument drawen, and presented unto them for this purpose; and yet (as it seemes) desiring rather to adde shall to the fire of the subjects discontent, than quench the same, they did forbeare to give any notice thereof to the people.</p>
            <p n="8">8 After this certaine dangerous, and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious petitions contrived by the advice, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of the said Sir <hi>VVilliam Parsons,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>Adam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oftus,</hi> Sir <hi>Iohn Clotworthy</hi> knights, <hi>Amb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs Hill</hi> Esquier, and sundry others of the malignant party, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:42945:9"/> signed by many thousands of the malignant par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the Citie of <hi>Dublin,</hi> in the province of <hi>Vlster,</hi> and in sundry other partes in this kingdome, dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the Commons house in <hi>England,</hi> were at publicke asseizes, and other publicke places made knowne and read to many persons of qualitie in this kingdome, which petitions contayned mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters destructive, to the said Catholickes, their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, lives and estates, and were the more to be feared by reason of the active power of the said Sir <hi>Iohn Clotworthy</hi> in the Commons house in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> in opposition to your Majesty, and his bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous and inhumane expressions in that house against Catholicke Religion, and the professors thereof. Soone after, an order conceived in the Commons house of <hi>England,</hi> that no man should bowe unto the name of IESVS (at the sacred sound whereof all knees should bend) came to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the said Catholickes, and that the said malignant party did contrive, and plot to extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish their Religion and Nation, hence it did arise that some of the said Catholickes begun to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the deplorable and desperate condition they were in, by a Statute-law here found among the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of this kingdome, of the second yeare of the raigne of the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> but never
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:42945:10"/> executed in her time, nor discovered till most of the members of that Parliament were dead, no Catholicke of this kingdome could enjoy his life, estate or libertie, if the said statute were executed, whereunto no impediment remayned, but your Majesties prerogative, and power which were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to be clipped, or taken away as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore rehearsed, then the plot of destruction, by an Army out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and another of the malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant party in <hi>England</hi> must be executed, the feares of those twofold destructions, and their ardent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to mantayne that just prerogative, which might encounter and remove it, did necessitate some Catholickes in the North about the two and twentieth of <hi>October</hi> 1641. to take Armes, in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynance of their Religion, your Majesties rights, and the preservation of life, estate, and liberty, and immediately thereupon, tooke a solemne Oath, and sent severall declarations to the Lords-Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices and Counsell to that effect, and humbly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sired they might be heard in Parliament, unto the determination whereof they were ready to submit themselves, and their demaunds, which declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being received, were slighted by the said Lords-Iustices, who with the swaying part of the said Counsell, and by the advice of the said two
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:42945:10"/> impeached Iudges, glad of any occasion to pur off the parliament which by the former adjourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was to meete soone after, caused a Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be published on the three and twentieth of the said Moneth of <hi>October</hi> 1641. therein accusing all the Catholickes of <hi>Ireland</hi> of disloyaltie, and thereby declaring that the Parliament was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogued, untill the sixe and twentieth of <hi>February</hi> following, within a few dayes after the said three and twentieth day of <hi>October</hi> 1641. many Lords and other persons of ranke and qualitie, made their humble adresse to the Lords-Iustices and Counsell, and made it evidently appeare unto them, that the said prorogation was against Law, and humbly besought the Parliament might sit, according the former adjournment, which was then the onely expedient to compose or remove the then growing discontents and troubles of the land; And the said Lords-Iustices, and their party of the Counsell, then well knowing that the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of both houses throughout the kingdome, (a few in and about <hi>Dublin</hi> onely excepted) would stay from the meeting of both houses, by reason of the said prorogation, by proclamation two dayes before the time, gave way the Parliament might sit, but so limitted that no Act of grace or
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:42945:11"/> any thing else for the peoples quiet, or satisfaction might he propounded or passed, and thereupon a few of Lords and Commons appeared in the Parliament house, who in their entrance at the Castle-bridge and gate, and within the yard to the Parliament house-dore, and recesse from thence, were invironed with a great number of Armed men, with their match lighted, and Muskets pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sented even to the breasts of the members of both houses, none being admitted to bring one servant to attend him, or any weapon about him, within the Castle-bridge, yet how thyn soever the houses were, or how much over-awed, they both did sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicate the Lords-Iustices and Counsell, that they might continue for a time together, and expect the comming of the rest of both houses, to the end they might quiet the troubles in full Parliament, and that some Acts of security granted by your Majestie, and transmitted under the great Seale of <hi>England,</hi> might passe to setle the mindes of your Majesties subjects, to these requests, so much conducing to your Majesties service, and the setlement of your people, a flat denyall was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the said Lords-Iustices and their party of the Counsell, by their working with their party in both houses of Parliament being then verie thyn
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:42945:11"/> as aforesaid, propounded an order should be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in Parliament that the said discontented Gentlemen tooke Armes in rebellions manner, which was resented much by the best affected of both houses, but being awed as aforesaid and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly informed of some particular persons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them, stood in opposition thereunto, that the said Musketiers were directed to shoote them at their going out of the Parliament house, through which terror, way was given to that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Notwithstanding all the before mentioned provocations, pressures, and indignities, the farre greater and more considerable party of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes, and all the Cities and Corporations of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and whole provinces stood quiet in their houses, whereupon, the Lords-Iustices and their adherents well knowing that many powerfull members of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> stood in opposition to your Majesty, made their principall application, and adressed their dispatches full fraught with calumnies, and false suggestions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Catholickes of this kingdome to them, and propounded unto them to send severall great forces to Conquer the kingdome, those of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant party here, were by them armed, the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes were not onely denyed Armes, but were
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:42945:12"/> disarmed, even in the Citie of <hi>Dublin,</hi> which in all successions of ages past, continued as loyall to the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> as any Citie or place whatso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, all other ancient and usuall Cities and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate Townes of the kingdome by meanes whereof principally the kingdome was preserved in former times were denied armes for their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to defend themselves: and expresse order given by the said Lords Iustices, to disarme all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks in some of the said Cities, and Townes, others disfurnished, were inhibited, to provide Armes for their defence, and the said Lords-Iustices and Counsell having received an order of both houses of Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> to publish a proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of pardon, uto all those who were then in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion (as they tearmed it) in this kingdome, if they did submit, by a day, to be limited. The said <hi>Sir VVilliam Parsons</hi> contrary to this order so wrought with his partie of the Councell, that a Proclamation was published of pardon, onely in two Counties, and a very short day prefixed, and therein all free-holders were excepted: through which every man saw that the estates of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks were first aymed at, and their lives next: The said Lords-Iustices and their partie having advanced their designe thus farre, and not finding
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:42945:12"/> the successe answerable to their desires, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Sir Charles Coote</hi> Knight and Barronnet, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceased, to march to the Countie of <hi>VVickloe,</hi> where he burnt, killed, and destroyed, all in his way. And in a most cruell manner, man, woman and child, persons, that had no appearing wills to do hurt, nor power to execute it; soone after some foot-compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies did march in the night by direction of the said Lords-Iustices, and their said partie, to the Towne of <hi>Sawntry</hi> in <hi>Fingall,</hi> three miles of <hi>Dublin;</hi> a Countrey that neither then, nor for the space of foure or five hundred yeares, before did feele, what troubles were, or warre meant, but it was too sweet and too neere, and therefore fit to be forced to armes; in that towne innocent husband-men, some of them being Catholicks, and some Protestants, taken for Catholicks, were murthered in their Inne, and their heads carried triumphant into <hi>Dublin;</hi> next morning complaint being made of this, no redresse was obtained therein, whereupon some Gentlemen of qualitie, and others the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Countrey, seeing what was then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and what passed in the said last march towards the Countie of <hi>VVickloe,</hi> and justly fearing to be all murthered, forsooke their houses, and were constrained to stand together in their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:42945:13"/> though ill provided of Armes or ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Hereupon a Proclamation was agreed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at the Councell-boord on the thirteenth of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> 1641. and not published or Printed till the fifteenth of <hi>December,</hi> by which, the said Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and <hi>George King</hi> by name, were required to come in, by or upon the eighteenth of the said Moneth and a safty was therein promised them. On the same day, another Proclamation was pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished summoning the Lords dwelling in the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish-pale,</hi> neere <hi>Dublin,</hi> to a grand-Councell on the seventeenth of the said Moneth, but the Lords Iustices, and their party of the Counsell to take away all hope of accommodation, gave direction to the said Sir <hi>Charles Coote,</hi> the said fifteenth day of the said Moneth of <hi>December</hi> to march to <hi>Clon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarffe</hi> being the house, &amp; Towne of the said <hi>George King,</hi> and two miles from <hi>Dublin,</hi> to pillage, burne kill, and destroy all that there was to bee found, which direction was readily and particularly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served (in manifest breach of publicke faith) by meanes whereof the meeting of the said Grand-Councell was diverted, the Lords not daring to come within the power of such notorious faith-breakers, the consideration whereof, and of other matters aforesaid, made the Nobility and Gentry
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:42945:13"/> of the <hi>English-pale,</hi> and other parts of the province of <hi>Leinster</hi> sensible of the present danger, and put themselves in the best posture they could, for their naturall defence, and imployed Lieutenant Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonell <hi>Red,</hi> to present their humble Remonstrance to your Sacred Majesty and to declare unto you the state of their affaires, and humbly to beseech reliefe and redresse therein, the said Lieutenant-Colonell though your Majesties servant and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in publicke trust (in which case the Law of Nations affoords safety and protection) was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out regard to eyther, not onely stopped from pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in his imployment, but also tortured on the racke at <hi>Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 The Lord-president of <hi>Munster</hi> by directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the said Lords-Iustices (that province be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing quiet) with his accomplices, burnt, preyed, and put to death Men, Women, and Children, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out making any difference of quality, condition, age, or sex in severall parts of that province. The Catholickes, Nobles and Gentlemen there mistru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted and threatned, and others of inferior qualitie trusted and furnished with Armes, and ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The province of <hi>Connaght</hi> was used in the like measure, whereupon, most of the considerable Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes in both the said provinces were inforced (without Armes or ammunition) to looke after safety, and to that end to stand on their defence,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:42945:14"/> still expecting your Majesties pleasure, and alwaies ready to obey your commands, Now the plot of the said ministers of state and their adherents, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing even ripe, applications were incessantly by them made to the malignant party in <hi>England,</hi> to deprive this people of all hopes of your Majesties justice or mercie, and to plant a perpetuall enmity betweene the <hi>English</hi> and <hi>Scottish</hi> Nation and your subjects of this kingdome.</p>
            <p n="11">11 That wheras, this your Majesties kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> in all successions of ages, since the raigne of King <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>second,</hi> sometimes King of <hi>England</hi> and Lord of <hi>Ireland,</hi> had Parliament of their owne composed of Lords and Commons in the same manner and forme, qualified with equall liberties, powers, priviledges, and immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties with the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant of the King and Crowne of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and for all that time no prevalent Record, or authenticke president can be found, that any Statute made in <hi>England,</hi> could or did bind this kingdome before the same were here established by Parliament, yet upon untrue suggestions and informations given of your subjects of <hi>Ireland,</hi> an Act of Parliament intituled an act for the speedy, and effectuall reducing of the rebels in his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties kingdome of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to their due obedience to his Majestie, and the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:42945:14"/> another Act intituled an act for adding unto and explayning the said former Act, was procured to be enacted in the said Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> in the 18. yeare of your Majesties raigne, by which Acts, and other proclamations your Majesties subjects unsumoned, unheard, were declared Rebels and two Millions and a halfe of Acres arrable, med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and profitable pasture within this kingdome were sould to undertakers, for certaine summes of money, and the edifices, Loghes, Woods, Bogs, wastes &amp; their appurtenances were thereby men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to be granted and past gratis, which Acts the said Catholickes doe conceive to have beene forced upon your Majesty, and although voyde, and unjust in themselves, to all purposes, yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue matters of evill consequence, and extreame prejudice to your Majesty, and totally destructive to this Nation. The scope seeming to ayme at Rebels onely, and at the disposition of a certayne quantity of Land, but in effect and substance, all the Lands in the kingdome, by the words of the said Acts may be distributed in whose possession soever they were without respect to age condition or quality, and all your Majesties Tenures, and the greatest part of your Majesties standing Revenew in this kingdome taken away, and by the said Act if it were of force, all power of pardoning, and of granting those Lands, is taken from your Majesty,
<pb facs="tcp:42945:15"/> a president that no age can instance the like, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst this Act the said Catholickes doe protest, as an Act against the fundamentall Lawes of this kingdome, and as an Act destructive to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties right, and prorogatives, by colour whereof most of the forces sent hither to infest this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome by Sea and Land disavowed any authoritie from your Majesty but doe depend upon the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 All strangers and such as were not inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Citie of <hi>Dublin,</hi> being commaunded by the said Lords-Iustices, in and since the said Moneth of <hi>November</hi> 1641. to depart the said Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie were no sooner departed then they were by the direction of the said Lords-Iustices, pillaged a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad and their goods seized upon; and confiscated in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and they desiring to returne under the protection and safety of the state, before their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance in any action, were denyed the same, and divers other persons of ranke &amp; quality by the said Lords-Iustices imployed in publicke service, and others keeping close within their doores without annoying any man, or syding then with any of the said Catholickes in Armes, and others in severall parts of the kingdome, living under, and having the protection, and safety of the state, were sooner pillaged; their houses burnt, themselves, their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and servants killed, and destroyed than any
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:42945:15"/> other, by directions from the said Lords-Iustices, and by the like direction, when any Commaunder in chiefe of the Army promised or gave quarter or protection, the same was in all Cases violated, and many persons of qualitie, who obtayned the same, were ruyned before others. Others that came into <hi>Dublin,</hi> voluntarily, and that could not be justly suspected of any crime, if <hi>Irishmen,</hi> or Catholickes, by the like direction were impriso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in <hi>Dublin,</hi> robbed and pillaged abroad, and brought to their tryall for their lives; The Citie of <hi>Dublin</hi> and <hi>Corke,</hi> and the ancient Corporate Townes of <hi>Drogheda, Yeoghell,</hi> and <hi>Kinsale.</hi> who voluntarily received Garrizons in your Majesties name, and the adjacent countries, who releived them were worse used and now live in worse con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition than the <hi>Isralites</hi> did in <hi>Egipt:</hi> So that it will be made appeare, that more murthers, breaches of publicke faith, and quarter, more destruction and desolation more cruelly not fit to be named, were committed in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the direction, and advice of the said Lords-Iustices and their party of the said Counsell, in lesse than eighteene Moneths, then can be paralleled to have beene done by any Christian people.</p>
            <p n="13">13 The said Lords-Iustices, and their adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, have against the fundamentall Lawes of the Land, procured the sitting of both houses of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
<pb facs="tcp:42945:16"/> for severall Sessions (nine parts of ten of the naturall and genuine members thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing absent) it standing not with their safety, to come under their power, and made up a conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable number in the house of Commons, of clerks, souldiers, serving men, and others not legally, or not chosen at all, or returned, and having no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of estate within the kingdome, in which sit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting sundry orders were conceived, and dismisse obtayned of persons before impeached of Treason in full Parliament, and passed or might have pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed some Acts against Law, and to the prejudice of your Majesty, and this whole Nation, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring these troubles, Tearmes were kept, and your Majesties Court of chiefe-place, and other Courts sate at <hi>Dublin</hi> to no other end or purpose, but by false and illegall Iudgements, Outlawries, and other Capitall proceedings, to attaynt many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sands of your Majesties most faithfull subjects of this kingdome, they being never summoned, nor having notice of those proceedings, and Sheriffes made of obscure meane persons, by the like practise appointed of purpose, and poore Artificers Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-souldiers, and mecanicall servants returned Iurors, to passe upon the lives, and estates of those who came in upon protection and publicke faith.</p>
            <p n="14">14 Therefore, the said Catholickes in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of themselves, and of the whole kingdom of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:42945:16"/>
               <hi>Ireland</hi> doe protest &amp; declare against the said procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, in the nature of Parliaments, and in the other Courts aforesaid, &amp; every of them, as being heynous crimes against Law, destructive to the Parliaments, &amp; your Majesties prerogatives, and authoritie &amp; to the rights, &amp; just liberties of your most faithfull subjects.</p>
            <p>Forasmuch dread Soveraigne as the speedy appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of apt remedies unto these grievances, &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy pressures, will tend to the settlement, &amp; improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your Majesties revenew, the prevention of further effusion of bloud, the preservation of this kingdome from desolation, &amp; the content and satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of your said subjects, who in manifestation of their duty and zeale to your Majesties service, will be most willing &amp; ready to imploy 10000. men, under the conduct of wel-experienced Commanders in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of your Royall rights and prerogatives. They therfore, most humbly beseech your Majestie that you will vouchsafe gracious answers to these their hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and just Complaints. And for the establishment of your people in a lasting peace and securitie, the said Catholicks, do most humbly pray, that your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie may be further graciously pleased to call a free Parliament in this kingdome; in such convenient time, as your Majestie in your high wisdome shall thinke fit, and the urgencie of the present affaires of the said kingdome doth require; And that the said Parliaments be held in an indifferent place, summo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:42945:17"/> by, &amp; continued before some person or persons of honour, &amp; fortune, of approved faith to your Majesty &amp; acceptable to your people here, &amp; to be timely pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by your Majesty in this governmēt, which is most necessary for the advancement of your service &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent condition of the kingdom, in which Parliament, the said Catholickes doe humbly pray these &amp; other their grievances may be redressed, &amp; that in the said Parliament, a statute made in this kingdom in the 10. yeare of K. <hi>Henry</hi> the 7. commonly called <hi>Poynings Act,</hi> &amp; all acts explayning or inlarging the same, be by a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rticular act suspended, during that Parliament, as it hath been already don, in the 11 year of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> upon occasions of far lesse momēt than now do offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, And that your Majesty with the advice of the said Parliament will be pleased to take a course for the repealing, or further continuance of the said Statutes, as may best conduce to the advancement of your ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice here, &amp; peace of this your Realme, and that no matter whereof Complaint is made in this Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strance, may debarre Catholickes, or give interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to their free Votes, or Sitting in the said Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; And as in dutie bound they will ever pray for your Majesties long and prosperous Raigne over them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>